A Guide to the Dieter Hans Max Gröschel Collection, 1965-2004
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
A Guide to the Dieter Hans Max Gröschel Collection, 1965-2004
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-54
1 box, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 0.4 feet, 19 folders
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Dieter Hans Max Gröschel in 2010.
Biographical Information
Dieter Hans Max Gröschel was born in Würzburg, Germany, in 1931. After studies in Würzburg and Erlangen he graduated in Medicine from the University of Cologne in 1957. He did internships at the University of Cologne (1957-58), the U.S. Army Hospital Landstuhl, Germany (1958), and Lutheran Hospital Cologne (1958-59). His postgraduate work was at the University of Cologne in Neurosurgery (1959-60) and in Microbiology and Hygiene (1960-63).
He emigrated to the United States in 1963 and worked at the Wistar Institute in Philadelphia, PA, then joined the faculty of Microbiology of Temple University School of Medicine as assistant and associate professor in 1965. From 1968 to 1971 he served as Director of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases of Springfield Hospital Medical Center in Springfield, MA, with an appointment as clinical associate of the University of Connecticut School of Medicine in Hartford. In 1971 he accepted an appointment as associate professor of pathology at the M.D. Anderson Hospital and Tumor Institute in Houston, TX, with appointments in the UT Medical School and UT Graduate School. He was promoted to professor in 1978. From 1979 to his retirement as professor emeritus in 1996 he worked at the University of Virginia in the Departments of Pathology and Medicine.
Dr. Gröschel was licensed to practice medicine in Germany (1959), Pennsylvania (1965), Massachusetts (1969), Texas (1971), and Virginia (1979). He specialized in Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases and was board-certified by the American Board of Medical Microbiology. He was active in the American Academy of Microbiology, the American Society for Microbiology, and the Infectious Diseases Society of America. He authored over 200 publications in both English and German.
Research interests: Natural resistance to infection; rapid diagnosis, identification, and antimicrobial resistance of nosocomial microorganisms; prevention of hospital infections; antisepsis and disinfection; history of medicine.
Scope and Content
This collection contains certificates and plaques awarded to Dr. Gröschel. It also contains photos of several famous physicians and two medallions created to celebrate the founding of the American Society for Microbiology 75 years earlier. Four oversize documents are in the Diploma and Certificate Collection, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Department of Historical Collections and Services, MS 42 (http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=uva-hs/viuh00042.xml).
Arrangement
The files are arranged by type of item (certificate, medal, plaque, photo) and by date within the item type.
Contents List
- American Society for Microbiology, International Symposium on Chemical Germicides in appreciation of your hard work ..., n.d., certificate (Box-folder 001-001)
- American Society for Microbiology, distiguished service, n.d., certificate (Box-folder 001-002)
  Given for service as an Editorial Board Member of "Journal of Clinical Microbiology."
- The Educational Council for Foreign Medical Graduates, 1965 March 24, certificate (Box-folder 001-003)
- Hampden District of the Massachusetts Medical Society, membership, 1970 September 21, certificate (Box-folder 001-004)
- Texas State Board of Medical Examiners, license, 1971 December 7, certificate (Box-folder 001-005)
- American Academy of Microbiology, certificate of fellowship, 1973 February 9, certificate (Box-folder 001-006)
- American Society for Microbiology, Member of the Committee on Becton Dickinson Award, 1986 June 30, certificate (Box-folder 001-007)
- Instituto Nacional de la Nutricion, 1987 July 10, certificate (Box-folder 001-008)
- Infectious Diseases Society of America, elected fellow, 1989 September 16, certificate (Box-folder 001-009)
- American Medical Association, Physician's Recognition Award, 1994 April 1-1997 April 1, certificate (Box-folder 001-010)
- American Society for Microbiology, 40 year membership club, 2004 April 20, certificate (Box-folder 001-011)
- American Society for Microbiology, 75th anniversary, "The Jubilee Medallion as an Emblem of the American Society for Microbiology," 1974, bronze medallion, stand, and reprint of Medallion article (Box-folder 001-012)
  Medallion was made by the Medallic Art Company, N.Y. It is three inches in diameter and has mini medallions of protozoa, algae, bacteria, fungi and viruses on the face in relief.
- American Society for Microbiology, 75th anniversary, 1974, silver medallion and stand (Box-folder 001-013)
- American Society for Microbiology, service as Chairman, Committee on Laboratory Practices in Microbioloy, 1985-1990, 1990?, plaque (Box-folder 001-014)
- American Society for Microbiology, ABMM Professional Recognition Award, 1991, plaque (Box-folder 001-015)
- Ignaz Phillipp Semmelweis (1818-1865), 1860, photo of engraving (Box-folder 001-016)
  On the back of the photo is typed Ignaz Philipp Semmelweis (1818-1865). Radierung von E. Doby, o.O. 1860. Aus dem Inst. f. Gesch. d. Med., Wien.
- Max von Pettenkofer (1818-1901), n.d., copy of painting on board (Box-folder 001-017)
  On the back of the board is written Max von Pettenkofer Aus der Neumann-Sammlung des Hygiene-Institut Hamburg von Uta Burger 1980
- Robert Koch (1843-1910), n.d., black & white photo (Box-folder 001-018)
- Eli Metchnikoff (1845-1916), n.d., black & white photo (Box-folder 001-019)